<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Loues peereles paragon, or the attributes, and progresse of the Church A sermon preached in St. Maries in Oxford, and at Harfield in Middlesex. 1613. By Iosias Byrd.</title>
            <author>Bird, Iosias, d. 1666.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1613</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 7 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A17423</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 4242</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S107338</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99843040</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99843040</idno>
            <idno type="VID">7747</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A17423)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 7747)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1059:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Loues peereles paragon, or the attributes, and progresse of the Church A sermon preached in St. Maries in Oxford, and at Harfield in Middlesex. 1613. By Iosias Byrd.</title>
                  <author>Bird, Iosias, d. 1666.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 27, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Ioseph Barnes,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1613.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Cf. Folger catalogue, which gives signatures: A-D⁴ [E]² .</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The attributes, and progresse of the Church.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="engraved_title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:7747:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:7747:1"/>
            <p>PARTHENIA or THE MAYDENHEAD of the first musicke that <hi>euer was printed for the VIRGINALLS<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>COMPOSED</hi> By three famous Masters: William Byrd D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>: Iohn Bull, &amp; Orlando Gibbons Gentilmen of his Ma<hi rend="sup">ties</hi>: most Illustrious Chappell. Ingrauen by William Hole.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>depiction of a woman playing a virginal (keyed instrument)</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>Lond: print: for N<hi rend="sup">ris</hi> Dor: Euans: Cum priuilegio. Are to be sould by G. Lowe print<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in Lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 chunk">
                  <desc>…</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:7747:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:7747:2"/>
            <head>TO THE HIGH &amp; MIGHTY <hi>and magnificent Princes Frederick Electo Palatine of the Reine: and his betrothed Lady, Elizabeth the only daughter of my Lord the king.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>The virgin PARTHENIA (whilst yet I may I offer vp to your virgin Highnesses. To you (Gracious Lady euen from the byrth she was entended: and nowe I trust shalbe more wellcome hauing learnd to tune and twine togeith these next neighbour letters E and F. the vowell that makes so sweet a Consona<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. Her notes so linkt and wedded togeither seeme liuely Hierogliphicks of the harmony of mariage. the high and holy State wherinto you shortly must be incorporat. This smale worke (yet first in this kind) was only ment for this lesser world: howbeit under your shadowes (in yo<hi rend="sup">r</hi> sunneshine I should say rather; y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is, yo<hi rend="sup">r</hi> sweete and glorious Consorte it may sound &amp; rellish in the eares of the greater. For Musick like that miraculous tongue of the Apostles hauing but one and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> same Caracter is alike knowne to all the sundry nations of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world. And what wonder sine Harmony is the Soule thereof multipliciously varied of fowre bare notes as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Body is of the fowre Elements. These lessons were composed by three famous Masters in the faculties. whereof one had y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hono<hi rend="sup">r</hi> to be yo<hi rend="sup">r</hi> teacher most Illustrious lady; and had he not had it before thereby deserued the stile of a Doctor. If to theire great<hi rend="sup">r</hi> grace, yo<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Grace will vouchsafe to lend yo<hi rend="sup">r</hi> white hands they will arriue w<hi rend="sup">th</hi> more pleasure at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> princely eares of yo<hi rend="sup">r</hi> GREATE FREDERIKE. Our lord Iesus who hath honored mariage w<hi rend="sup">th</hi> his deere praesence and first miracle, extraordinarily do<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> instance of his mayden mother, aeternally blesse yo<hi rend="sup">u</hi> maydes and maryed.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yo<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Highnesses most humbly William Hole</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:7747:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:7747:3"/>
            <head>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. HVGH HOLLAND On his worthy frend W: H: &amp; his Triumuiri of Musicke.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>List to that sweete Recorder;</l>
               <l>How daintily this BYRD his notes doth vary,</l>
               <l>As if he were the Nightingalls owne brother!</l>
               <l>Loe where doth pace in order</l>
               <l>A brauer <hi>BULL</hi> then did Europacary:</l>
               <l>Nay ſet all Europe showe me such an other.</l>
               <l>Orlando though was counted Musicks fath<hi rend="sup">r</hi>;</l>
               <l>Yet this <hi>ORLANDO</hi> parallels di Lasso:</l>
               <l>Whose triple praise would tire a very Iasso;</l>
               <l>The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hecre in one these three men rather heare y<hi rend="sup">u</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And praise thaire songes: &amp; sing his praise who, maried</l>
               <l>Those notes so well w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> they so sweetely varied.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <head>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>: GEO: CHAPMAN In worthye loue of this new worck, and the most Autenticall Aucthors.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>By theis choice lessons of theise Musique Mast<hi rend="sup">rs</hi>;</l>
               <l>Ancient, and heightn'd w<hi rend="sup">th</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Arts full Bowles</l>
               <l>Let all ou<hi rend="sup">r</hi> moderne, mere Phantastique Tasters,</l>
               <l>(Whose Art but forreigne Noueltie extolls)</l>
               <l>Rule and confine theyr fancies; and prefer</l>
               <l>The consta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t right. &amp; depthe Art should Induce;</l>
               <l>To all lite flashes, by whose light they err;</l>
               <l>This wittie Age, hath wisedome least in use;</l>
               <l>The World, ould growing, Ould, w<hi rend="sup">th</hi> it, grow Men;</l>
               <l>Theyr skylls decaying, like theyr bodies streng<hi rend="sup">the</hi>;</l>
               <l>Yonge Men, to oulde are now out Childeren:</l>
               <l>First Rules of Art, encrease still w<hi rend="sup">th</hi> theyr leng<hi rend="sup">the</hi>.</l>
               <l>Which see in this new worck, yet neuer seene:</l>
               <l>Art, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> more oulde, growes eu<hi rend="sup">r</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> more greene.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="musical_composition">
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>Preludium.</head>
               <head>I.</head>
               <byline>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. William Byrde.</byline>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="music">
                     <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:7747:4"/>
               <head>Pauana. S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>: W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Petre</head>
               <head>II.</head>
               <byline>William Byrde</byline>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="music">
                     <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7747:4"/>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="music">
                     <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <trailer>finis</trailer>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:7747:5"/>
               <head>Galiardo.</head>
               <head>III.</head>
               <byline>William Byrde</byline>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="music">
                     <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <trailer>finis</trailer>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:7747:5"/>
               <head>Preludium</head>
               <head>IIII.</head>
               <byline>W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Byrde</byline>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="music">
                     <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:7747:6"/>
               <head>Galiardo M<hi rend="sup">ris</hi> Marye Brownlo.</head>
               <head>V.</head>
               <byline>Will: Byrde</byline>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="music">
                     <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7747:6"/>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="music">
                     <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:7747:7"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:7747:7"/>
               <head>Pauana. The Earle of Salisbury.</head>
               <head>VI.</head>
               <byline>Will: Byrde</byline>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="music">
                     <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="part">
               <head>Galiardo</head>
               <head>VII.</head>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="music">
                     <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:7747:8"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:7747:8"/>
               <head>Galiardo. Secundo M<hi rend="sup">ris</hi>: Marye Brownlo</head>
               <head>VIII.</head>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="music">
                     <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <byline>Will Byrde</byline>
               <trailer>finis</trailer>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:7747:9"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:7747:9"/>
               <head>Preludiu'</head>
               <head>IX.</head>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="music">
                     <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <byline>M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> D<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> Bull</byline>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:7747:10"/>
               <head>Pauana. S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>: Thomas Wake</head>
               <head>X.</head>
               <byline>D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>: Bull</byline>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="music">
                     <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7747:10"/>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="music">
                     <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:7747:11"/>
               <head>Galiardo. S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>: Thomas Wake</head>
               <head>XI.</head>
               <byline>D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>: Bull</byline>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="music">
                     <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7747:11"/>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="music">
                     <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:7747:12"/>
               <head>Pauana</head>
               <head>XII.</head>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="music">
                     <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7747:12"/>
               <p> 
                  <gap reason="music">
                     <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:7747:13"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:7747:13"/>
               <head>Galiardo.</head>
               <head>XIII.</head>
               <byline>D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>: Bull</byline>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="music">
                     <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:7747:14"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:7747:14"/>
               <head>Galiardo</head>
               <head>XIIII.</head>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="music">
                     <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:7747:15"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:7747:15"/>
               <head>Galiardo</head>
               <head>XV.</head>
               <byline>D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>: Bull</byline>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="music">
                     <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <trailer>finis</trailer>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:7747:16"/>
               <head>Galiardo</head>
               <head>XVI.</head>
               <byline>Orlando Gibbons</byline>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="music">
                     <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7747:16"/>
               <p> 
                  <gap reason="music">
                     <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:7747:17"/>
               <head>Fantazia of foure parts</head>
               <head>XVII.</head>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="music">
                     <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7747:17"/>
               <p> 
                  <gap reason="music">
                     <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <byline>Orl: Gib:</byline>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:7747:18"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:7747:18"/>
               <head>The lord of Salisbury his Pauin</head>
               <head>XVIII.</head>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="music">
                     <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <byline>Orl: Gib:</byline>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:7747:19"/>
               <head>Galiardo</head>
               <head>XIX.</head>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="music">
                     <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7747:19"/>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="music">
                     <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <byline>Orl: Gib:</byline>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:7747:20"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:7747:20"/>
               <head>The Queenes Com<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>and</head>
               <head>XX.</head>
               <byline>Orl: Gib:</byline>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="music">
                     <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:7747:21"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:7747:21"/>
               <head>Preludium</head>
               <head>XXI.</head>
               <byline>Orlando Gibbons</byline>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="music">
                     <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <trailer>Finis</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="modern_addenda">
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:7747:22"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:7747:22"/>
               <p>
                  <add>Pasted on back of title page of PARTHENIA (HN 14176)</add>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <add>
                     <gap reason="music">
                        <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </add>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:7747:23"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:7747:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>
                  <add>Verso of leaf pasted on back of dedicatory page of PARTHENIA (HN 14176)</add>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <add> The Gift of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. W<hi rend="sup">m</hi>. Plater 1769</add>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <add>Parthenia 1613</add>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
